Hello there and welcome back to the course, now in this lesson we're going to be exploring
a discriminated union which is a powerful pattern for modeling data that can take multiple
shapes. So whether you're working with form states or API responses or perhaps UI components,
discriminated unions helps us write safe, expressive code that adapts to different cases.
But what is a discriminated union? A discriminated union is a union of object types that
each share a common literal property and this is called a discriminant.
TypeScript uses that property to narrow type automatically. So with no further ado let's
pull up our code and let's get righting. So let's have a type of loading state and the
status is surprising enough loading. We're going to have that as a string. Now we can have
a second type and the second type is going to be a success state that also has a property
of status, that to success, but we're also going to give it another as the property and
it's going to have a property of data which we're going to set as a type of string.
I know it's great to declare a third type and this is going to be error state.
This also has a status property of error, surprisingly enough and we're going to give it a property
of error which is also a string. And now what we can do is we create another type called
fetch state and this is a union of the three types above. So we're going to have the loading state
and with a pipe character we then say it's also success state and it's also error state.
Okay so now it's combination of these three types. But what is the common property
between these three types? Well obviously it's status here. So this becomes discriminant for the union.
So let's now actually use as an example. So we're going to create a function
render and we have a parameter of state which is our fetch state.
And now we can do if state status is loading,
we just going to return loading and loading and loading.
Else we can then expect the status property again if state status equals success.
And to return, this time we're going to return dynamic string to data dollar,
whoops data dollar, state dot data.
Otherwise we can just going to return an error to error state dot error.
You can see as we are going through here that IntelliSense was picking up the
kind of doing logic through here and picking up the relevant property because it understood
that when we're coming into here that we are looking at the error state and the third
KOS, the error property. As we saw TypeScript automatically narrowed a type based on the stages value
and we didn't need to do any casting at all. So that's one of the advantages.
Why use discriminated unions? Well, the perfect for doing things like modeling state machines
or handling API responses, managing UI component states and writing exhaustive switch statements.
We could expand this loop function by adding the state never. So the never state in TypeScript,
as the name suggests, is for when you don't have a situation where you're not actually going
to return anything or return any sort of type. So for example, if you're throwing an error,
you might do throwing a new error and you're not actually going to return a type for that
particular function, maybe the function is going to return a Boolean or it's going to return a string
or an object, but you get an API error. So you were going to throw an exception and that's why
you could use the never state. So what we could do here is we could rewrite this to have a
switch statement. So we could do switch and we could look at the status property and we have a
cases for loading. Let's do our loading case. We're going to return loading and have the same for
the other cases as well. So we're going to try and copy and paste this for speed.
So it says that's going to be case loading. This is going to be success.
This case is going to be error. We're going to return error message. So error state dot error.
And now we're going to have our default case. So for a default case, we could grab a state check.
So we can do exhaust, say exhaust, div, check. That's a type of never. So we're defaulting this
state to the never state. So there's not actually going to have any actual state. That's what
it's called never. And then we can just simply return an exhaustive check here through it's all.
Now, what is this doing? Well, this is this pattern is sure that we've handled every single
possible case. So we have our loading case. We have our success and we have our error,
but we also then capture any other possible case. And because at the moment, we don't actually
have any other cases defined, we can set this to never. But then when we add a new state later,
types of script is going to alert us. So in summary, discriminated unions let us model
variant data with clarity and safety. So we've learned how to define them and how to narrow them
and enforce exhaustiveness. And in the next lesson, we're going to be looking at how to do
advance utility types by building our own type transformations.